<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Art on MadeByMe</title><link>https://madebyme.today/tags/art/</link><description>Recent content in Art on MadeByMe</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright &amp;copy;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 14:50:59 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://madebyme.today/tags/art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Art From Chaos</title><link>https://madebyme.today/articles/franklin/art-from-chaos/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 14:50:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://madebyme.today/articles/franklin/art-from-chaos/</guid><description>&lt;p>Making art is hard. Drawing pictures is tedious. With programming, however, we can automate things. The point of
automation is to reduce the amount of manual labor. So let&amp;rsquo;s mix evolution, DNA, and programming together to make art
that &lt;em>makes&lt;/em> itself. Pictures that &lt;em>draw&lt;/em> themselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="concepts-and-definitions">
Concepts and definitions
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#concepts-and-definitions" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Before we dive deep into making art, we need to understand some important concepts &amp;ndash; first things first.
&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;">Automatic art&lt;/span>&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, at its core, uses generic algorithms.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_algorithm">Wikipedia&lt;/a> has a really nice page about them, if you&amp;rsquo;d like to read
it. However for the sake of the article this is enough:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &lt;strong>Genetic Algorithm&lt;/strong> is an algorithm inspired by the process of natural selection used to find solutions for
optimization problems. It has three main parts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mutation&lt;/strong> - during which specimens are randomly changed,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Scoring&lt;/strong> - during which specimens are ranked by their &amp;ldquo;ability to adapt to their environment&amp;rdquo;,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Crossing&lt;/strong> - during which one or more specimens are mixed together to produce a new member.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>OK. ðŸ‘Œ&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With these terms out of the way, let&amp;rsquo;s try to understand how exactly it works. Imagine we need to find a solution
for a problem. It can be anything, like finding optimal timetable for a university class. Firstly, we need to encode a
solution as a series of bytes (their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_representation">Genetic representation&lt;/a>, if
you will). Once we have that we can clone the encoded representation to create a generation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each member of the generation will be randomly &lt;strong>mutated&lt;/strong> and then &lt;strong>scored&lt;/strong> based on how well they fit in our
constrains set. For example: we might want to have a timetable which leaves just enough break time to eat a quick lunch,
but not too much, so that we can go home earlier. This (and similar constrains) might be used to evaluate the value of
our new mutated timetable. With each specimen evaluated we leave a few of the best and discard the rest ðŸ’€.&lt;br>
The last step is to mix our &lt;em>special&lt;/em> timetables to create new ones to fill the generation again.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="./genetic-algorithm-cycle.webp"
alt="Genetic Algorithm Cycle"loading="lazy"
/>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>To mutate, to score, to kill, to breed, to continue the cycle of life. It might sound simple, but in reality it is
shockingly efficient in searching the solution space.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="art-from-evolution">
Art from evolution
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#art-from-evolution" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Alright. Now with the theory out of the way, let&amp;rsquo;s conceptualize a program for generating automatic art. Probably it&amp;rsquo;s
a good moment to explain the clickbaity summary at the top of this article: the pictures will not &lt;em>draw&lt;/em> themselves, the
goal is to make &lt;em>a program&lt;/em> which will generate art automatically. It&amp;rsquo;s going to be an iterative solution where each
cycle is parametrized by the results of its predecessor.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-0-initialization">
Step 0: Initialization
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#step-0-initialization" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Before we do anything towards evolution we need to prepare a generation first. So what&amp;rsquo;s our generation size? Let&amp;rsquo;s see
if Wikipedia has something insightful to say:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The population size depends on the nature of the problem, but typically contains several hundreds or thousands of
possible solutions.&lt;br>
~ &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_algorithm">Genetic algorithm @ Wikipedia&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Well, that&amp;rsquo;s really not the most helpful answer. ðŸ˜&lt;br>
It really boils down to this: the more specimen we have, the more memory the program requires and more CPU time to
process each generation. On the other hand, the more specimen a generation have, the wider portion of solution space it
can search. Whatever the generation size will be, we need to have a prototype - a specimen, which cloned will fill the
generation. Since we&amp;rsquo;re dealing with art here, a &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabula_rasa">tabula rasa&lt;/a>&lt;/em> should be a
fitting choice.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-1-mutation">
Step 1: Mutation
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#step-1-mutation" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Mutation method greatly affects the end result, so it&amp;rsquo;s imperative to select a right one. Mutation algorithms are
usually stateless, meaning modification of each specimen does not affect any other. In each iteration the mutator will
introduce a &lt;em>small&lt;/em> change into specimens&amp;rsquo; genetic representation. On images it can be, for example: changing random
pixels. This works, but the final image looks too detailed (in a bad way).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, the changes does not technically need to be &lt;em>small&lt;/em> per se, however applying too big changes might result in
overriding a portion of the genome that was making this particular specimen a good candidate, thus resulting in loosing
progress achieved by previous generations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=generating+images+with+genetic+algorithm">If you&amp;rsquo;d google &amp;ldquo;generating images with genetic algorithm&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>,
you&amp;rsquo;d find that most projects on the subject use geometric shapes when applying mutation. Simple onces, like
&lt;strong>circles&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>rectangles&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>triangles&lt;/strong> are a good choice. From these it&amp;rsquo;s rectangles, that can be the most
easily represented in code. Having said that let&amp;rsquo;s see how a single specimen might change over a few first iterations.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="./mutation-diagram.webp"
alt="Mutation diagram"loading="lazy"
/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>An exemplar of a 6-generation mutation process. Starting with generation 0 - no mutation applied, till generation 5 - five mutations applied.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>Each of the rectangles on that picture represents a random mutation applied onto the image, meaning that all information
needed to unambiguously identify a rectangle (width, height, coordinates of one of the corners, and its color) have been
randomly generated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The above illustrates the risk of allowing mutations which are not constrained by their impact: the mutation introduced
in 1&lt;sup>st&lt;/sup>
step has been almost fully overwritten after 5 mutations. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, the result
might be beneficial, but overall we want to utilize genome that have evolved in past generations, not to discard it
completely.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-2-scoring">
Step 2: Scoring
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#step-2-scoring" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Implementing scoring function can be tricky. Basically we need to have a way of mapping each specimen into an integer
value. Then with values for all specimens we can calculate a threshold and filter out all images above it. The genetic
algorithm does not provide to us any way of determining whether a mutation has been beneficial; that is strictly
depends on the implementation. So let&amp;rsquo;s talk about what it is exactly we&amp;rsquo;d like to achieve here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The idea behind generating images through evolution is that we have &lt;strong>an ideal&lt;/strong> to which we&amp;rsquo;re aiming to get as close
as possible. An original image, from which will derive a collection of images &lt;em>similar&lt;/em> to it, each mutated and scored
multiple times. A scoring function could calculate a difference between the original image and the one being currently
scored:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ f(O, S) = \sum_{i=0}^n | O_n - S_n | \tag{1} $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both &lt;code>O&lt;/code> and &lt;code>S&lt;/code> refer to a collection of pixels representing the original image and the current specimen respectively,
thus allowing us to index their pixels and calculate a difference between them. This, on its own, isn&amp;rsquo;t the most helpful
piece of advice, as it glides over the fact that we a calculating a difference of &lt;em>pixels&lt;/em> not numbers, we cannot do
arithmetics on them. To fix that we need to be a bit more clever here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can utilize the fact that pixels are just color, usually represented in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RGB_color_model">RGB&lt;/a> notation. Each color in the RGB color space is represented by three
numbers from 0 to 255 (each encoding the amount of red, green, and blue). Numbers on their own don&amp;rsquo;t have any meaning,
its the context that makes them colors, points, or geometric shapes. If we&amp;rsquo;d interpret these three numbers as
coordinates in three-dimensional space, then they would become points. In that case, the difference between two points
can be implemented as the distance between then:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ d(A, B) = \sqrt{(x_2 - x_1)^2 + (y_2 - y_1)^2 + (z_2 - z_1)^2} $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Alright ðŸ‘Œ. The final thought: this formula calculates the difference between two points in space, but we don&amp;rsquo;t
really need &lt;em>the distance&lt;/em>, just &lt;em>an indication&lt;/em> of how similar the two pixels are. Since calculating a square root on
computers is expensive, we can remove that bit and we&amp;rsquo;re left with:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ g(A, B) = (x_2 - x_1)^2 + (y_2 - y_1)^2 + (z_2 - z_1)^2 \tag{2} $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By combining (1) and (2) together we get:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$ f(O, S) = \sum_{i=0}^n | (r_2 - r_1)^2 + (g_2 - g_1)^2 + (b_2 - b_1)^2 | $$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That was a bit more mathsy that I&amp;rsquo;ve initially anticipated &lt;code>â—•_â—•&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="step-3-crossing">
Step 3: Crossing
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#step-3-crossing" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the last step the algorithm has to fill up &lt;em>almost&lt;/em> emptied generation. This step, quoting Wikipedia, it&amp;rsquo;s:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[&amp;hellip;] a genetic operator used to combine the genetic information of two parents to generate new offspring. [&amp;hellip;]
Solutions can also be generated by cloning an existing solution, which is analogous to asexual reproduction.&lt;br>
~ &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossover_(genetic_algorithm)">Crossover (genetic algorithm)&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>There are several ways we can make it work, from naive ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>create an exact copy of one of the remaining images,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>create a mutated copy of one of the remaining images,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>split image into two halves and fill it with a respective half from one of the two parents,&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>to more sophisticated ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>for each pixel pair taken from two parents calculate an arithmetic average and use it to construct a new pixel,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>for each pixel pair taken from two parents calculate an weighted average and use it to construct a new pixel.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The methods mentioned above differ in their complexity, but more importantly, in how fitting specimens they create. It&amp;rsquo;s
worth to mention that in opposition to the previous two steps, this one isn&amp;rsquo;t strictly mandatory. The algorithm will
still work without it and the generated images will look acceptable. With &lt;strong>crossing&lt;/strong>, however the algorithm generates
more fitting specimens, relative to a one without the 3&lt;sup>rd&lt;/sup>
step, in the same number of
generations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We will take a look at several of &lt;strong>crossing&lt;/strong> methods mentioned above and we will plot scores of their specimens as a
function of generation number, to see how well they perform. ðŸ“ˆ&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">
Next steps
&lt;a class="anchor" href="#next-steps" aria-label="Anchor">
&lt;span class="inline-svg">&lt;svg width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">&lt;path fill="none" d="M10.6666 13.3333 10.0808 12.7475c-.78102-.7811-.78102-2.0474.0-2.82845l4.5049-4.50489C15.3668 4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 17.4142 5.41415l1.1715 1.17157C19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 8.6331 18.5857 9.41415L16.9999 10.9999m-3.6666-.3333L13.919 11.2524c.7811.7811.7811 2.0474.0 2.8284L9.41415 18.5857C8.6331 19.3668 7.36677 19.3668 6.58572 18.5857L5.41416 17.4142C4.63311 16.6331 4.63311 15.3668 5.41416 14.5857l1.58578-1.5858" stroke="#393636" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"/>&lt;/svg>
&lt;/span>
&lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the first article from a series about generating art through genetic algorithms. In the next articles &lt;em>(coming
up soon-ish)&lt;/em> we&amp;rsquo;ll turn those ideas into &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/">Rust&lt;/a> code and after that we&amp;rsquo;ll finally make art
that makes itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;figure class="border">&lt;img src="./brett-jordan-M3cxjDNiLlQ-unsplash.webp"
alt="Order and Chaos"loading="lazy"
/>&lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Photo by &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/@brett_jordan?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Brett Jordan&lt;/a> on &lt;a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/M3cxjDNiLlQ?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>See you around!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ðŸŒŠ&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Term coined by me. If you want to read more about art generated by algorithms you should probably look for
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_art">Algorithmic art&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>